João Zão

Android Engineer Born 1989 in Esposende, Portugal



About me

I am a devoted Android Engineer, an **Electrical and Computer Engineer with** great enthusiasm in computer science. Simply love structure and order, therefore I also stand for quality - quick learner and really love to share knowledge so, working in a team is always a joy for me. Eager to learn, I'm regularly reading, listening or trying to help others. Addicted to best practices, always aiming to deliver rock SOLID, clean and readable code or any other task where it applies like documentation.

I've been playing with Android since 2010 but "only" in 2014 I've started to deep dive into it professionally. In 2017 I fell in love with Kotlin, started to advocate it inside the company and in the GDGPorto local community by giving some talks. In the last year I've been also using it to share business logic across multiple platforms. I'm curious by nature, so I've been keeping an eye into flutter as well and already used it in some company internal applications.

Skills



Contact

Esposende, Portugal

immbzao@gmail.com

00351 919238221

joaozao.com

(joaobzao

Experience

Android Engineer

Blip

2016 - Currently

Blip is a pure technological hub responsible to build all of the major applications for Paddy Power Betfair, one of the biggest betting companies in the world. I've been developing a lot of Android applications and libraries for the entire group always with high code standards with scalability and readability in mind. Lately, brought kotlin multiplatform to the table and since then I've been building one of the core layers of our applications in a way that it could be shared among other platforms as well. The projects I'm dealing with at blip allowed me to polish my skills in the following areas -Android, Java, Kotlin, Gradle, MVP, MVVM, Jetpack, Dl..

Android Engineer

TOPDOX

2015 - 2016

A multi-cloud platform and file manager that allowed to seamlessly deal with all the files(local and cloud) with a built-in docx and gdoc collaborative editor made in-house. I was responsible to build the Android app, unfortunately the startup no longer exists, which means that the app can't be found in the play store anymore. Part of our tech stack was bought by Dropbox. During the development of this app I faced a lot of challenges related to build a file manager targeting a wide range of Android versions and some devices from weird manufacturers with unexpected behaviours. Also spent a lot of time thinking and designing effecient ways to sync clouds with endless files and folders, as well as thinking about caching mechanisms. Tech - Android, Java, MVP, Dagger 2, SQLite, JUnit 4, Espresso...

Mobile Engineer/IoT

CimSoft

2014 - 2015

Responsible to design a home automation system(ZigBee protocol) and to build an Android app to control home devices such as car garage, doors, lamps... Google maps integration and used Android location API for several configurable behaviours. Also built an application for lawyers so they could manage all the files of their lawsuits in an easy manner. Tech - Android, Java, MVP, SQLite.. C++ and C# in the hardware parts.



Education

MSc in Electrical and Computers Engineering @ FEUP 2008 - 2013

Major in Robotics, specialization in IoT and mobile communications.



Extras

Kotlin for Java Developers

Although I had some experience with kotlin when this course was announced several Droidcons (London, Turin, at KotlinKonf 2018 I took it anyway. It's a great course from Jetbrains that helped me consolidate my knowledge. https://www.coursera.org/account/acc omplishments/verify/WXJXMX9W94H4

Green Robot enthusiast

I already had the chance to go to Krakow, Lisbon...) I'm an active participant in the GDG Porto local community events and even helped organize one of the Android Sessions at Blip. Had the Pleasure to share some stuff with the community by giving a talk in one of the Android Sessions. https://twitter.com/gdgporto/status/98 9806969891508224